Guide to the Charles Augustus Ropes Dimon Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Charles Augustus Ropes Dimon papers
1863-1907
WA MSS S-1308
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.5
(8 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence and military papers documenting the military career of Charles Dimon in 1864-65.
Dimon, Charles Augustus Ropes, 1841-1902
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was purchased from Robert Black in 1959 on the William Robertson Coe Fund for Western Americana.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
CHARLES AUGUSTUS ROPES DIMON (1841-1902)
Charles Augustus Ropes Dimon was born in Fairfield, Connecticut in 1841 and moved to Salem, Massachusetts in 1859. He joined the Massachusetts volunteer militia in April 1861, was mustered out in August, and enlisted at Lowell, Massachusetts in September as adjutant of the 30th Massachusetts Infantry. During 1861 and 1862 Dimon saw action in several battles, including the bombardment of Fort Jackson and St. Philip and the capture of New Orleans.
Dimon was promoted to major in the 2nd Louisiana Infantry United States Volunteers, but resigned due to poor health in June 1863. In 1864 he re-enlisted at Point Lookout, Maryland. While serving there and at Norfolk, Virginia, Dimon organized and commanded a volunteer regiment of former Confederate soldiers popularly known as the "Galvanized Yankees." On his recommendation and to encourage rebel prisoners to enlist, the regiment became the 1st United States Volunteer Infantry.
After successfully completing raids out of Norfolk, Dimon was promoted to colonel in August 1864. On orders from General Grant, he traveled with the 1st United States Volunteer Infantry to Fort Rice, Dakota Territory, in the fall of 1864. He commanded Fort Rice for one year with orders to suppress hostile Indians and encourage peaceful trade. Difficulties were encountered with the Blackfoot, Yanktonai, and Onkpapas Indians, who threatened attacks and stole horses, but Dimon was able to secure a general peace.
In July 1865, Dimon became afflicted with chronic laryngitis and left Fort Rice on doctor's orders. After he recovered he was assigned to Lawrence, Kansas, with orders to control mutinous troops. On August 10, 1865, Dimon received a commission as brevet brigadier general and in November 1865 was mustered out of service at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas.
In 1866, Dimon became the military chief of police in Mobile, Alabama, and in 1869 he married Kate Thompson of Morristown, New Jersey. Returning to Lowell, Massachusetts, he served as alderman and then mayor for two years. He died in Lowell in 1902.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Augustus Ropes Dimon Papers contain correspondence and documents pertaining to Dimon's military career, particularly his recruitment of "Galvanized Yankees" in Maryland and Virginia and his subsequent command of Fort Rice in Dakota Territory. The papers cover the period from 1864 to 1907, but the bulk of material dates from 1864 and 1865.
The papers are arranged in three series. Series I, Correspondence, is contained in Boxes 1 and 2. Boxes 3 to 6 house Series II, Military Papers, and Box 7 holds Series III, Other Papers. Oversize material is located in Box 8.
Series I, Correspondence, contains chronologically arranged correspondence covering a variety of military and family subjects. In addition to Dimon, correspondents include General Benjamin Butler, General John Pope, General Alfred Sully, and Captain Benjamin Dimon, Charles's younger brother. The recruitment of Confederate prisoners of war for the United States Army and the establishment of the 1st United States Volunteer Infantry are discussed in Dimon's early correspondence. In a letter of March 19, 1864 to General Butler, Dimon suggested designating the recruited prisoners' regiment as Infantry to encourage more enlistments. General Butler complied with Dimon's request and established the regiment under Dimon's command. Dimon also discussed the defense of Norfolk-Portsmouth, the dangers of smallpox, scurvy, and scarlet fever.
In later letters Dimon described the transporting of troops to Fort Rice, a desolate outpost, located in the driest part of Dakota territory. Scurvy, due to lack of fresh vegetables, was rampant and Dimon also wrote about health problems caused by extreme cold weather. In correspondence with General Sully, official policies concerning friendly and hostile Indians are discussed. Dimon was ordered to protect friendly Indians, to encourage trade, and to deliver swift retribution in case of attack. Dimon discussed the use of Indian scouts for mail and reconnaissance. Other topics addressed include the sale of whiskey and ordnance to the Indians, attack by hostile Indians, ongoing peace negotiations, and fights among various Indian tribes.
As commander of Fort Rice, Dimon was responsible for ordnance supplies, and his letters frequently refer to discrepancies between his records and those of the War Department. He mentioned court-martial proceedings, specifically the execution of a deserter, Private William Dowdy. Dimon also touched on such issues as the breadth of martial law at Fort Rice, the condition of neighboring forts, and steamship traffic along the Missouri River.
Dimon's correspondence with his family and fiancée, Sarah Braden, covers the social life of Salem and Lowell, Massachusetts, the death of their friend Captain Wheeler, and the end of Dimon's engagement to Sarah Braden. Dimon and his brother, Benjamin, who was stationed at Fort Berthold, Dakota Territory, discussed the poor conditions of that fort, peace negotiations with the Indians, and the maintenance of peaceful and lawful trade.
Series II, Military Papers, contains a variety of official papers covering Dimon's service in Virginia and North Dakota in 1864 and 1865. Papers concerning the court-martial of Enoch A. Adams include charges, specifications, and minutes of proceedings; Adams, editor of the Frontier Scout at Fort Rice, was charged with slandering Dimon, encouraging soldiers to desert, and frequenting a house of "ill-fame." Also included are charges, specifications, and minutes of Private Dowdy's court-martial. The depositions provide additional information relating to court-martials. A mutilated issue of Frontier Scout, Vol. I [No. 2], is included.
The maps detail winter routes between Fort Rice and Fort Sully and distances between other Dakota Territory forts. The map of Nebraska, Dakota Territory, and Montana marks the locations of United States military posts. Also included are ground and building plans for Fort Rice.
Dimon's memorandum books contain lists of steamship arrivals and departures, notations on mail delivery, and a handful of daily entries. The muster rolls list members of companies B, C, D, E, H, and K of the 1st United States Volunteer Infantry for 1864 and 1865. The forms indicate enlistment date, location of enlistment, years in service, and last day of pay.
General and special orders document the purpose and intent of the military presence in Dakota Territory. Orders from the Department of Virginia and North Carolina, Department of Norfolk-Portsmouth, Department of the North West, and printed orders from the United States War Department are included. Internal regimental orders issued by Dimon also appear. Ordnance records are found in a variety of forms, including abstracts, inventories, invoices, quarterly returns, receipts, and requisitions. Together these records provide information on the ordering and shipping of supplies, supplies held in store, and procedures for distribution and return of supplies. The records include documentation from Norfolk, Virginia, and Fort Rice. Dimon maintained a journal and kept some cryptic notes on a raid he led outside Norfolk, Virginia. Also included in the series are quartermaster store records and miscellaneous receipts from Norfolk and Fort Rice.
Series III, Other Papers, is arranged alphabetically by material type and spans the dates 1864-1907. Dimon's commission as brevet brigadier general and his official discharge are filed here. An unsigned essay, "Disloyal Preaching," chastises ministers who did not uphold constitutional principles. A copy of the Journal of the Military Service Institute, 1907, contains an obituary of Thomas Howard Ruger. Dimon's lecture, "Army life Among the Hostile Indians in Dakota Territory, 1864-1865," includes reminiscences of his Fort Rice command. A memorandum, prepared after Dimon's death, provides a detailed biography of Dimon's military and civilian careers. Also present are two works by Enoch G. Adams, "Wilderness [Expressions]," and an untitled poem.
Fort Berthold (N.D.); Courts-martial and courts of inquiry -- United States; Dakota Indians -- Wars, 1862-1865; Frontier and pioneer life; Indians of North America -- Commerce; Indians of North America -- North Dakota; Martial law -- United States; Military bases -- United States; Ordnance; Prisoners of War; Scurvy; Fort Rice (N.D.); Missouri River; North Dakota -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Prisoners and prisons; Depositions -- United States; Military orders -- United States; Muster rolls -- United States; Soldiers -- United States; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893; Dimon, Benjamin; Dimon, Charles Augustus Ropes, 1841-1902; Pope, John, 1822-1892; Sully, Alfred, 1821-1879; Diamond family; United States. Army -- Health and hygiene; United States. Army ( Military life); United States. Army. Volunteer Infantry, 1st (1864-1865)
- Correspondence, 1863-1902; Series I; 1; (2 Boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged chronologically. Undated correspondence and letter fragments are placed at the end of the series.
  - Correspondence, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Jan (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Feb (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Apr (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Correspondence, 1864 May (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Jun (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Jul (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Aug (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Sep (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Oct (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 191
  - Correspondence, 1864 Nov (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence, 1864 Dec (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Jan (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Feb (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
    See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 192
  - Correspondence, 1865 Mar (Box 1, Folder 34-36)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Apr (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - Correspondence, 1865 May (Box 2, Folder 39-42)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Jun (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Jul (Box 2, Folder 48-52)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Aug (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Sep (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Oct (Box 2, Folder 55-56)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Nov (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, 1865 Dec (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence: letter book, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence: letter book, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, 1866-68 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 63-64)
  - Correspondence: fragments (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Military Papers, 1864-1865; Series II; 2; (4 Boxes)
  Series II, Military Papers, is arranged alphabetically by subject and then chronologically.
  - Court Martials
    - Adams, Enoch G., 1865 Oct (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Dowdy, William, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Michie, James C., 1865 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Pease, F. D., 1864-65 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Upton, William B., 1865 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Depositions
    - Archibald, H. C., 1865 Oct (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Dimon, C. A. R., 1865 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Edwards, R. A. E., 1865 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - LaBarge, Joseph, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Miscellaneous depositions, 1865, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Ordnance depositions, 1864-65 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Southall, Luther, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Guest register: Fort Rice, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Journal: promotion list, document and ordnance receipts, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Lists, miscellaneous, 1864-65, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 80-81)
  - Maps
    See also: Oversize, Box 8, folders 193-97
    - Dakotah Territory; list of distances, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Nebraska, Dakota, and Montana (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Report on Cheyenne River, Cherry River, Craw Creek, Little Missouri, and Powder River, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Winter route between Fort Rice and Fort Sully, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Memorandum books, 1864-65,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 86-88)
  - Muster rolls
    See also: Oversize, Box 8, folders 198-209
    - Muster-in, 1864 May 6 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Muster-in, 1864 Aug 13 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Muster-out, 1864 Aug 13 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Note book, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Orders
    - Department of Missouri: printed, 1864-65 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - General Curtis, 1865 Oct 5 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Headquarters, Department of the Northwest, 1864 Aug (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Headquarters, Department of Virginia and North Carolina, 1864 Mar-Aug (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Headquarters, District of Kansas, 1865 Sep (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Headquarters, District of Iowa, 1865 Jan (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Headquarters, Expedition Purgo, 1864 Jun (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Headquarters, Norfolk and Portsmouth, 1864 May-Jun (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Headquarters, North Western Indian Expedition, 1864-65 (Box 4, Folder 101-03)
    - Headquarters, Post Commandant, 1864 Dec (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Index books, 1864-65 (Box 4, Folder 105-06)
    - War Department; printed, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 107-08)
  - Ordnance records
    - Abstract of articles, 1864 Apr (Box 4, Folder 109-10)
    - Abstract of expenditures, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Abstract of materials consumed, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Abstract of receipts, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 113)
      See: Oversize, Box 8, folders 210-11
    - Board of survey proceedings, 1865 Mar (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Inventories, 1864-65, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115-20)
    - Invoices, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 121-30)
    - Invoices, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 131-33)
    - Quarterly returns, 1864-65, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134-38)
    - Receipts, 1864-65, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 139-57)
    - Receipt journals, 1864-65 (Box 6, Folder 158-59)
    - Requisitions, 1864, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Reports, 1864 May 7 (Box 6, Folder 161)
  - Printed Works: Frontier Scout, Vol. 1 [No. 2], [1865] (Box 6, Folder 162)
  - Quartermaster's stores
    - Inventories, 1864 Mar-May (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Monthly returns, 1864 Mar-Apr (Box 6, Folder 164)
  - Receipts, 1864-65, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 165-79)
  - Report: Purgo Expedition, 1864 Jun 14-18 (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Whiskey sales: Fort Rice, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 181)
- Other Papers, 1863-1907; Series III; 2; (2 boxes)
  Series III, Other Papers, is alphabetically arranged by subject or title.
  - Certificates: discharge, 1865 Nov 22 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    See also: Oversize, Box 8, folders 212-14
  - Commission: Brevet Brigadier General, 1865 Aug 10 (Box 7, Folder 183)
  - Essay: "Disloyal Preaching", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 184)
  - Journal of the Military Service Institution No. 148, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 185)
  - Lecture: "Army Life Among the Hostile Indians in Dakota Territory 1864-65," General Charles A. R. Dimon, [1901] (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - Memoriam: Brevet Brigadier General Charles Augustus Ropes Dimon, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 187)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1864-65, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 188)
  - Poem: untitled, [Enoch G. Adams], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 189)
  - "Wilderness [Expressions]," Enoch G. Adams, 1865-66 (Box 7, Folder 190)
- Oversize
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence, 1864 Oct 27 (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Correspondence, 1865 Feb 5 (Box 8, Folder 192)
  - MILITARY PAPERS
    - Maps
      - Dakotah Territory, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 193)
      - Plans for Fort Rice, 1864 Jul (Box 8, Folder 194)
      - Plans for Fort Rice, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 195-97)
    - Muster rolls
      - Company "B", 1864 (Box 8, Folder 198)
      - Company "C", 1864-65 (Box 8, Folder 199-200)
      - Company "D", 1864-65 (Box 8, Folder 201-02)
      - Company "E", 1864-65 (Box 8, Folder 203-04)
      - Company "H", 1864-65 (Box 8, Folder 205-06)
      - Company "K", 1864 (Box 8, Folder 207)
      - Field and staff, 1864-65 (Box 8, Folder 208-09)
    - Ordnance records
      - Abstract of expenditures, 1865 (Box 8, Folder 210)
      - Abstract of provisions (Box 8, Folder 211)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Certificates: provisional commissions, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 212-214)